Finding Aid for Daniel Katz papers 1925-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Daniel Katz papers 1925-1997
Katz, Daniel, 1903-1998
90190 Aa 2
Professor of psychology at the University of Michigan, known for his work in social psychology, organizational behavior and race relations; papers document his teaching and research activities 1925-1997, and involvement in professional organizations.
9 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was received in three accessions, the first as part of the University of Michigan Department of Psychology record group, (Donor no. 5883 ) the second from Jean Katz Corwardine and Joanna Katz (Donor no. 8715, and the third form Katz's office at the Institute for Social Research (Donor no. 7399 ).
The collection is open for research.
University of Michigan psychology professor Daniel Katz was a nationally recognized scholar in the fields of social psychology and organizational behavior; he also made major contributions to the study of national attitudes and race relations. He is perhaps best known as the co-author (with Robert L. Kahn) of The Social Psychology of Organizations, which was published in 1966 and is widely considered to have been a seminal work in the discipline of social psychology.
Katz was born in Trenton, New Jersey on July 19, 1903. He received his BA from the University of Buffalo in 1925, and then enrolled at Syracuse University where he earned an MA in 1926 and a Ph.D. in Social Psychology in 1928. He married Christine Ross Braley in 1930, and they had two daughters.
Between 1928 and 1943, Katz was on the faculty of Princeton University's Psychology Department; he left in 1943 to become the first chairman of the Department of Psychology at Brooklyn College. During the Second World War he served as research director for the Division of Surveys of the Office of War Information, and as a research analyst for the War Department. Katz and a number of the social scientists he worked with during the war years formed the core of the Institute for Social Research (ISR) at the University of Michigan.
In 1947, Katz became director of ISR, where he researched human relations and management practices, including the role of worker participation in decision-making. Simultaneously, Katz became a professor of psychology. With Theodore Newcomb, he was instrumental in developing Michigan's doctoral program in social psychology. The Katz-Newcomb Lecture, an annual University event established in 1970, honors both professors.
Professor Katz carried out much of his research abroad, visiting Norway as a Fulbright scholar in 1951, and returning as a National Science Foundation Senior Fellow in 1957. As part of "A Study of National Attitudes and Values," Katz worked at the Belgrade Center from 1968 to 1969, where he directed field surveys in four Yugoslav republics. He also worked in Greece during this period, and was visiting professor at the University of Aarhus, Denmark from 1971 to 1972.
Over the course of his career, Katz published numerous articles and co-authored several books. He also edited or served on the editorial board of a variety of journals, including Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology, Personnel Psychology, and Public Opinion Quarterly. Katz was an adviser to the John Wiley Company psychology section during the 1960s and early 1970s, serving as editor of the publisher's Foundations of Social Psychology series.
Katz was active in several professional organizations, including the American Psychological Association, the Industrial Relations Research Association, the Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, and the Organization for Comparative Social Relations. On his retirement from the University of Michigan in May 1974, Katz was named Professor Emeritus of Psychology.
Katz died February 28, 1998 in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Daniel Katz's papers document his research and teaching activities from 1925 to 1997. His papers reflect the major issues and trends in social psychology, from its early development through its edification as a discipline. The development of Katz's thinking and work is illuminated through his extensive correspondence with contemporaries, articles and other publications, and research materials.
The Katz collection is divided into nine series: Personal; Professional Correspondence; Office of War Information; Professional organizations and related; Research and Surveys; Teaching and course materials; Articles; Published/Unpublished Materials; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Katz, Daniel, 1903-1998; Nationalism.; Organizational behavior.; Social psychology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Personal
  Biographical information and photographs of Katz are in the Personal series (1926-1995), as are Katz's notes as a student at Syracuse University.
  - Autobiographical Reminiscences undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Newcomb, Mary 1995 (Box 1)
    (comments upon her death)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Retirement from University of Michigan 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    includes photographs
  - Syracuse University, Notes from "Social Seminar," circa 1926-1928 (Box 1)
  - University of Buffalo Commencement Invitation 1925 (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence
  Professional Correspondence is divided into one chronological subseries and three topical subseries. The dates of the files within this series overlap because the materials were received from different sources at different times. The series documents Katz's involvement with professional organizations and his relationship with other colleagues. Katz maintained correspondence with a number of prominent social psychologists. He considered Floyd H. Allport his mentor and also exchanged personal letters with Professor Edwin Holt, who taught at Princeton. Correspondence with Richard Schanck documents one of Katz's early collaborations with a colleague.
  Katz's correspondence as an editor for John Wiley provides a sense of social psychology's development as a discipline, particularly during the 1960s. His critiques of colleagues' manuscripts serve to document the changing directions and priorities of an evolving social science. The Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues files include discussions by Katz and others about the role which social scientists should -- or should not -- play in becoming actively involved in social issues of the day. Of particular interest is the Herbert Kelman file, which documents Katz's defense of a friend and colleague who was denied a Fulbright fellowship in 1959 due to his pacifist views.
  - By date
    - 1925-1972, 21 folders (Box 1)
    - 1973-1996, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - By correspondent/topic 1945-1972
    (includes related papers)
    - Contemporary Psychology, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    - Dawes, Robyn 1970 (Box 2)
    - Goldman (Eric): editorship of Public Opinion Quarterly, April-May 1945 (Box 2)
    - John Wiley and Sons, Publishers
      - 1965-1972, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Foundations of Social Psychology Series 1963-1971 (Box 2)
    - Kelman, Herbert-Fulbright Case 1959 (Box 2)
    - The Social Psychology of Organizations, 1965-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues (SPSSI)
      - Psychology of Social Change, Yearbook 1942, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Secretary's correspondence 1946, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (Katz was secretary)
      - 1950-1969 (Box 2)
      - Lewin Memorial Award Committee 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - October 1973-April 1975 (Box 2)
  - By correspondent/topic 1973-1980
    - American Psychological Association July 1973-January 1974 (Box 2)
    - Athenian Institute of Anthropos 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - International Society of Political Psychology January-May 1978 (Box 2)
    - Organizational Psychology February 1976 (Box 2)
    - Publishers November 1973-July 1980 (Box 2)
  - By correspondent/topic 1931-1996
    - Allport, Floyd H. 1931-1946 (Box 2)
    - Back, Kurt et al. 1970-1976 (Box 2)
      (regarding Social Psychology)
    - Family 1938-1958, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fielding Institute, Review of HOD Program in Social Psychology 1989 (Box 3)
    - Gutek, Barbara 1986-1993 (Box 3)
    - Holt, Edwin 1936-1946 (Box 3)
    - Hyman, Herbert
      - 1951-1952 (Box 3)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - John Wiley and Sons, Inc.
      - Manuscript Reviews
        - Mankin, Donald 1974-1977 (Box 3)
        - Mednik, Higgins, and Kirschenbaum manuscript 1972-1974 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
          - 1976-1978 (Box 3)
        - Raven, Bertram and Rubin, Jeff 1973-1975 (Box 3)
      - Revision of Social Psychology of Organizations, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Blair 1995-1996 (Box 3)
      (regarding Floyd Allport)
    - Jossey-Bass Inc. Publishers, Review of Bolman and Deal Understanding Organizations, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Kahn, Robert 1990-1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Krech, David 1949-1950 (Box 3)
    - Reimer, Everett 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Sage Publications American Behavioral Scientist Special Issue, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Schanck, Richard and "Squint," 1937-1944, undated (Box 3)
    - Vallance, Ted 1951-1952 (regarding How Psychological Warfare Works) (Box 3)
- Office of War Information
  The Office of War Information series (1942-1944) is comprised of materials from Katz's tenure as the director of research at that department. It includes the raw data, reports, code books, and surveys themselves from a range of studies concerning public perception of World War II.
  - Memoranda December 17, 1942-July 18, 1944, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletter Current Surveys, April 1943-July 1944 (Box 3)
  - Project Proposals and Internal Correspondence 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Publications (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - May 25, 1942-July 21, 1942 (Box 3)
    - July 28, 1942-December 5, 1942, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Special Reports May 29, 1942-October 21, 1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Studies October-November 1942 (Box 4)
  - Surveys
    - Data from Survey 113 (Box 4)
    - Master Code Book
      - Survey S-17 (Box 4)
      - Survey S-18 (Box 4)
      - Survey 107 (Box 4)
      - Survey 122 (Box 4)
      - Survey 124 (Box 4)
      - Survey 125A (Box 4)
      - Survey 125B (Box 4)
      - Survey 126 (Box 4)
      - Survey 131 (Box 4)
    - Supplement to National Total Book (Box 4)
- Professional organizations and related
  The Professional organizations and related series documents Katz's participation in various professional conferences and the awards he received from different organizations. Of particular interest are transcripts from interviews with Katz about his career and the founding of the Institute for Social Research.
  - Awards
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences 1989 (Box 4)
    - American Association for Public Opinion Research (AAPOR) 1985 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1979-1995 (Box 4)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Fellowship 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Conferences
    - Battelle Conference on Critical Issues in Social-Program Evaluation 1973 (Box 4)
    - International Conference on Subjective Culture, Athens, Greece 1968 (Box 4)
    - International Public Opinion Research (IPOR) Conference in Paris 1952 (Box 4)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews Symposium 1955 (Box 4)
    - Symposium to Honor Robert Kahn 1989 (Box 4)
  - Interviews with Katz
    - Apfelbaum, Erika and Ian Lubek 1977 (Box 4)
    - Veraff, Joseph, Oral History of ISR undated (Box 4)
  - Katz-Newcomb Lecture Programs 1973-1995 (Box 4)
- Research and Surveys
  Katz's diverse research interests are evident in the Research and Surveys series. The series contains research papers by Katz, surveys he designed, research grant proposals, and correspondence with colleagues and former students regarding research in progress. At the broadest level, Katz was interested in relations between national and ethnic groups, and in people's attitudes towards social change; a synopsis of Katz's research objectives may be found in the "National Science Foundation Grant" research proposal.
  The records in this series also show how Katz adapted his interests to a variety of situations: desegregation in the United States, voting patterns in Denmark and Norway, ethnicity in Yugoslavia. The surveys indicate how public opinion polls were developed, the types of questions which were asked, and in the case of the "National Role Project (Yugoslavia)," how raw survey data was interpreted.
  - 1952-1973
    - American Council for Behavioral Sciences in the Kibbutz 1969 (Box 5)
    - American Psychological Association (APA) 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Borre, Ole (University of Aarhus, Denmark) 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - Desegregation Research Project Proposals 1952-1954 (Box 5)
    - Ford Foundation-Social Science Research Proposals 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - "The Future of Organizations," paper by Katz circa 1969 (Box 5)
    - Kibbutzim 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - National Role Project (United States) 1962-1966, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - National Role Project (Yugoslavia) 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - National Science Foundation Grant, "A Continuing Study of Social Change," 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Norway-Institute for Social Research 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - Organization for Comparative Social Research (OCSR) 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - Party Identification Surveys (Denmark and Norway) 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Public Opinion Survey (Greece) 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - "Some Theoretical and Methodological Issues in Cross-Cultural Research," paper by Katz, circa 1967 (Box 5)
  - 1938-1982
    - AIR University European Research Group 1951-1952 (Box 5)
    - AT&T
      - Correspondence and Research 1982 (Box 5)
      - Proceedings of the Conference on Organization Factors Relevant to Bottom-Line Performance 1982 (includes photograph) (Box 5)
    - Danish Election Survey 1971 (Box 5)
    - Norway
      - Election Study 1957-1958
        - Interview Translation (Box 5)
        - Leadership Questions (Box 5)
        - Local Voter Codes (Box 5)
        - Nationwide Analysis (Box 5)
      - Norway and the European Common Market 1976 (Box 5)
    - Princeton University Office of Public Opinion Research
      - Anti-Semitism Study for American Jewish Committee
        - Memoranda and Data 1942 (Box 5)
        - Report 1943 (Box 5)
      - Interest-Values Inventory
        - Statement of Objective 1938 (Box 6)
        - Surveys 1939 (Box 6)
      - Measuring the Intensity of Opinion 1942 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous Reports 1942 (Box 6)
      - Trends of Opinion During First Year of War undated (Box 6)
    - Public Opinion Quarterly, Election Predictions, United States Presidential Race 1944 (Box 6)
    - University of Denver National Opinion Research Center
      - Negro Questionnaire, Correspondence 1944 (Box 6)
      - Sampling Procedures 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan
      - Center for Conflict Resolution
        - Chicago Daily News article, 1966 (Box 6)
        - Correspondence and Project Proposals 1959 (Box 6)
        - National Role Project 1963 (Box 6)
        - Project Proposals 1960, 1967, undated (Box 6)
      - Greek Nationalism Study 1968 (Box 6)
      - Institute for Social Research (ISR) 1972-1976
        - 1973 Spring Omnibus (Box 6)
        - Codebooks-Phase I and II April-June 1973 (Box 6)
        - Instruction Book and Interviewer's Booklet, Spring 1973 (Box 6)
        - Memorandum January-August 1973 (Box 6)
        - Rational and Design for research project on Attitudes Toward Public Agencies June-December 1972 (Box 6)
        - Election Study-1976 Questionnaire 1976 (Box 6)
        - Quality of Service Measurement Program (Bureaucratic Encounters)
          - Correspondence and Research Proposal 1972-1974 (Box 6)
          - Follow-up Proposals 1975 (Box 6)
          - Reviews 1975-1977 (Box 6)
      - Party Organization, Social Structure and Political Behavior in the Detroit Area 1959-1960 (Box 6)
      - Undergraduate Grades and the Miller Analogies Test as Predictors of Graduate Success 1960 (Box 6)
      - Yugoslav Nationalism Study 1968 (Box 6)
- Teaching and course materials
  Katz's role as professor is documented in the Teaching and course materials series, where exams, handwritten lecture notes, and syllabi are available.
  - Non-University of Michigan
    - Aquinas College, Guest Lecturer 1985 (Box 7)
    - Brooklyn College
      - Psychology 54.5, Fall 1943 (Box 7)
      - Social Psychology 31 1944-1946 (Box 7)
    - Denmark, Basic Concepts in Social Psychology 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    - Finland Lectures undated (Box 7)
    - Princeton University
      - Psychology 29/513: Seminar in Social Psychology 1937-1942 (Box 7)
      - Psychology 303: Seminar in Social Psychology 1937-1941
        - Lecture Notes (Box 7)
        - Syllabi and Exams (Box 7)
      - Psychology 304: Psychology of Social Institutions 1937-1941
        - Lecture Notes (Box 7)
        - Syllabi and Exams (Box 7)
      - Psychology 521 (Personality) 1940-1941 (Box 7)
      - "Trial and Error Learning," Lecture for Professor Langfeld's Course 1929 (Box 7)
    - South Orange-Maplewood Adult School, Social Psychology 1936 (Box 7)
    - Undated
      - Psychology 250: A Psychological Approach to Social Science (Box 7)
      - Social Psychology 185: Introduction to Survey Research (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan
    - Psychology Courses
      - 62/262 1947-1949 (Box 7)
      - 262: Social Psychology, Spring 1950 and Winter, 1960 (Box 7)
      - 143, Summer 1953 (Box 7)
      - 145, Spring 1953 (Box 7)
      - 153 1958-1960 (Box 7)
      - 202, Spring 1956 and Spring, 1957 (Box 7)
      - 267: Social Psychology, Spring 1951 and Spring, 1953 (Box 7)
      - 268: Social Psychology and "Social Problems," Fall 1954 (Box 7)
      - 270: Research Methods in Social Psychology 1955-1956
        - Lecture Notes (Box 7)
        - Syllabus and Materials (Box 7)
      - 278, Spring 1957 and Fall, 1959 (Box 7)
      - 373: Seminar in Social Psychology, Fall 1950 (Box 7)
      - 374: Perception, Winter 1951 (Box 7)
      - 581: Attitudes and Behavior, Spring 1962 (Box 7)
      - 681: Basic Concepts of Social Psychology 1963-1965 (Box 7)
      - 682: Advanced Social Psychology 1963-1972 (Box 7)
      - 782: Organizational and Collective Behavior, Winter 1967-Fall 1969 (Box 7)
      - 782: Psychological Aspects of Social Systems, Fall 1970 and Winter, 1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 888: Social Psychological Aspects of International Relations 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Psychology Department
      - Program Evaluation Report circa 1974 (Box 7)
      - Important Books on Psychology Questionnaire undated (Box 7)
      - Student Movements on Campus 1971, undated (Box 7)
- Writings and Lectures
  Dated articles in the Writings and Lectures series (1927-1997) are arranged chronologically; those undated are in alphabetical order, as are lectures. Note that Katz's numerous book reviews and editorials are compiled into folders and are dated by the earliest document. Many of this collection's articles are co-written, but additional authors are not noted here. Also included is a bibliography for materials published before 1980.
  - Bibliography 1927-1979 (Box 7)
  - Reviews of Katz's writings 1955-1985 (Box 7)
  - Articles written (arranged by date)
    - 1927 Economic Radical Movements (Box 7)
    - 1928 The Syracuse University Reaction Study, Doctoral Thesis, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1931-1988 Book Reviews (Box 7)
    - 1943 Absenteeism (Box 7)
    - 1947 Psychological Barriers to Communication (Box 7)
    - 1948 A Long Range Program for the Study of Group Motivation, Group Morale and Group Performance (Box 7)
    - 1949
      - An Analysis of the 1948 Polling Predictions (Box 7)
      - Good and Bad Practices in Attitude Surveys in Industrial Relations (Box 7)
      - Morale and Motivation in Industry (Box 7)
    - 1950
      - The Influence of the Group Upon Social Behavior and Attitudes (Box 7)
      - Survey Techniques in the Evaluation of Morale (Box 7)
    - 1951
      - Human Organization and Worker Motivation (Box 7)
      - Social Psychology and Group Processes (Box 7)
    - 1952
      - Leadership Practices in Relation to Productivity and Morale (Box 7)
      - Some Recent Findings in Human Relations Research (Box 7)
    - 1954
      - Public Opinion and Propaganda (Box 7)
      - Research in Human Relations and Organizations (Box 7)
      - Satisfactions and Deprivations in Industrial Life (Box 7)
    - 1957
      - Establishing an Effective Motivational Pattern (Box 7)
      - The Measurement of Ego Defense as Related to Attitude Change (Box 7)
    - 1958 Organizational Effectiveness and Change: An Evaluation of SPSSI by Members and Former Members (Box 7)
    - 1959
      - Consistent Reactive Participation of Group Members and Reduction of Intergroup Conflict (Box 8)
      - The Reduction of Intergroup Hostility: Research Problems and Hypotheses (Box 8)
    - 1960
      - A Comparative Study of the Social Psychology of Nationalism (Box 8)
      - Current and Needed Psychological Research in International Relations (Box 8)
      - The Functional Approach to the Study of Attitudes (Box 8)
      - Undergraduate Grades and the Miller Analogies Test as Predictors of Graduate Success (Box 8)
    - 1961
      - Dynamic Properties of Organizations and the Principle of Maximization (Box 8)
      - The Impact of Local Party Activity Upon the Electorate (Box 8)
    - 1962 Human Interrelationships and Organizational Behavior (Box 8)
    - 1962-1967 Editorials, Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology and Journal of Personality and Social Psychology (Box 8)
    - 1963 The National Role: Some Hypotheses About the Relation of Individuals to Nation in America Today (Box 8)
    - 1964 The Motivational Basis of Organizational Behavior (Box 8)
    - 1965
      - Psychological Studies of Communication and Persuasion (Box 8)
      - The Social Psychology of Conflict (Box 8)
    - 1966 Attitude Formation and Public Opinion (Box 8)
    - 1968 Consistency for What? The Functional Approach (Box 8)
    - 1969
      - A Comparative Approach to the Study of Nationalism (Box 8)
      - On the Nature of National Involvement: A Preliminary Study (Box 8)
    - 1971
      - Organizations in a Changing World (Box 8)
      - Social Psychology: Comprehensive and Massive (Box 8)
    - 1972 The Rights of the Individual in Modern Society (Box 8)
    - 1973
      - Factors Affecting Social Change (Box 8)
      - Party Identification and Its Motivational Base in a Multiparty System: A Study of the Danish General Election of 1971 (Box 8)
      - Types of Feedback in Relation to the Functioning of Social Systems (Box 8)
    - 1974
      - Alienation and Support for the Political System (Box 8)
      - Feedback in Social Systems: Operational and Systemic Research on Production, Maintenance, Control and Adaptive Functions (Box 8)
      - Integration, Effectiveness and Adaptation in Social Systems: A Comparative Analysis of Kibbutzim Communities (Box 8)
        (Part 1 of 2)
      - Social Change from the Perspective of Open System Theory (Box 8)
      - Utilization and Evaluation of Government Services by the American People (Box 8)
    - 1975
      - Americans Love Their Bureaucrats (Box 8)
      - Integration, Effectiveness and Adaptation in Social Systems: A Comparative Analysis of Kibbutzim Communities (Box 8)
        (Part 2 of 2)
    - 1976 Survey Methodology: Its Development, Utilization and Potential (Box 8)
    - 1977 Organizations as Social Systems (Box 8)
    - 1978 Social Psychology in Relation to the Social Sciences: The Second Social Psychology (Box 8)
    - 1981
      - In Memoriam: Angus Campbell 1910-1980 (Box 8)